Hi, this is Matt Baker. Exactly 7 years
ago on this date, we released one of our
most popular videos ever. Who would be
king of America if George Washington had
been made a monarch? Now, obviously, the
title wasn't meant to be taken seriously
because the United States has never
actually [clears throat] been interested
in having a king. And in fact, to this
day, is very much against it. But that's
okay because the video was really just
an excuse to delve into the family tree
of George Washington and to learn a bit
of history. Well, since it's been 7
years and since I've recently learned
several extra things about his tree, I
thought it would be a good idea to do a
sort of update or part two, especially
considering that on this particular 4th
of July, the US is celebrating its 250th
anniversary. So, what better time to
take a closer look at the country's main
founder.
Okay, so the first thing I need to
remind you of is that George Washington
did not have any biological children of
his own, at least not that we know of,
which is why figuring out who his heir
would be today is very tricky. In my
previous video, I suggested three
different hypothetical scenarios. One
based on the line of his older
half-brother, Augustine. One based on
the line of his adopted son, George
Washington Parke Custis. And one based
on the line that inherited his Mount
Vernon estate. Of these three lines, the
one that a lot of people found the most
surprising was the middle one. So, let
me refresh your memory about it. Around
30 years before he became president,
George Washington married a wealthy
widow named Martha, whose first husband,
Daniel Parke Custis, had died 2 years
previously. Martha had four children
with her first husband, but only one of
these survived to become an adult, a son
named John Park Custis. A year before
the Revolutionary War broke out, John
married Eleanor Calvert and fathered
several children with her. But then,
just 2 weeks after the surrender at
Yorktown, he died, probably from typhus
contracted at a military camp. At this
point, his two youngest children, George
and Nelly, were adopted by their
grandmother, Martha, as well as their
step-grandfather,
George Washington, who went on to become
the first US president. Now, here's the
interesting thing.
G.W.P. Custis had only one child with
his wife, Mary, who lived to adulthood,
a daughter named Mary. And that Mary
went on to wed Robert E. Lee, the famous
Confederate General. Thus, if George
Washington had become king, and if he
had named his adopted son as his heir,
and if everything else had stayed the
same, meaning same marriages and same
births, which is actually really
unlikely, but if all of these things
were true, it would be the descendants
of Robert E. Lee who would wear the
crown today. Take note that at the time
of my first video, Robert E. Lee IV was
still living, but has since passed away,
meaning that the heir of George
Washington through this line is now his
son, Robert E. Lee V. This time, I've
opted not to share his photo or any
information about him, and I've done
likewise for all the other living people
on this tree because, after all, they
deserve their privacy. So, don't go
trying to contact any of these people to
tell them to claim their throne.
Now, going back to G.W.P. Custis, one
extra thing that I recently learned
about him was that in real life, he
likely had a pretty close connection to
real royalty. You see, the father of
Eleanor Calvert was Benedict Calvert,
who might have been an illegitimate
grandchild of King George I. Now, while
the Washington family itself, as well as
most Americans, are descended from
royalty, if you go back far enough, very
few descend from a king as recent as
George I. So, in other words, George
Washington Parke Custis may have been,
in real life, a tiny bit royal.
However, as I mentioned in the previous
video, if George Washington had been
made king, I think it would have been
very unlikely that his adopted son would
have been named his heir. That's because
in real life, George Washington left a
very detailed will, and in it he
basically revealed who he trusted the
most. Although he left many relatives
bequests, the bulk of his estate,
including his main property at Mount
Vernon, as well as all of his personal
papers, went to just one person, his
nephew Bushrod Washington, who, I might
add, also happened to be a US Supreme
Court Justice.
Now, Bushrod, which I mistakenly
pronounced Bushrod last time, to the
amusement of many, is a rare name. So,
let me take a moment to explain where it
comes from. In this case, it was the
maiden name of Bushrod's mother. In Old
English, a rod means a clearing. So,
basically, Bushrod has the same meaning
as Bushfield, which, by the way, was the
name of the Bushrod Plantation. Now,
last time I said that Bushrod Washington
didn't have any children. I'm going to
come back to this later, but for now,
take note that what I should have said
was that he didn't have any official,
meaning white, children. This is why,
after his death, the Mount Vernon estate
went to his nephew, John A. Washington
II, and then on to John A. Washington
III, who was the final member of the
family to own the property. You see,
although in some alternative timeline,
John A. Washington III might have been
King John, and Mount Vernon may have
been turned into a palace, in real life,
what happened was that in 1858, John A.
Washington III sold the president's
former residence to a charity called The
Mount Vernon's Ladies Association. And
this charity has operated it as a
historical site ever since. However, if
that hadn't happened, and if this line
had been the monarchs of the USA,
[clears throat]
there would have been three more King
Johns, and then finally a Queen Mary.
Now, again, at the time of the original
video, Mary Shaffner was still living.
However, she has since passed away,
meaning that the heir of George
Washington through this line is now her
son, Larry.
Now, one other real-life thing to note
about John A. Washington III is that he
fought in the Civil War on the side of
the South. In fact, all of the close
relatives of George Washington, 12 in
total, fought for the Confederacy, which
is something that a lot of people find
quite surprising. But really, it
shouldn't be, nor should be the
connection to Robert E. Lee, because
after all, the Washingtons were from
Virginia, and virtually all of them,
George Washington [clears throat]
included, were enslavers.
Which brings me back to Bushrod
Washington. In 1802, after the death of
First Lady Martha Washington, Bushrod
officially inherited and moved into
Mount Vernon. With him came around 80
enslaved individuals, one of whom was a
mixed-race man named West Ford. In 1805,
Bushrod gave West Ford his freedom and
appointed him manager of Mount Vernon, a
post which he held until it was taken
over by the Ladies Association. Now, the
only thing we know for sure about
Westford's parentage was that his mother
was a woman named Venus, who was
enslaved by John A. Washington, the
father of Bushrod. However, it has been
claimed that the father of Westford was
none other than George Washington. But,
it's important to note that most
historians disagree with this for
several reasons. First, it is widely
believed that the first president was in
fact sterile, meaning that he was unable
to produce any children. The health
reasons for which continued to be
debated. Second, Venus was enslaved at
Bushfield, which was owned by George's
brother John, not at Mount Vernon. So,
it's much more likely that Westford was
fathered by either John or by one of his
sons. Third, because Bushrod in
particular gave Westford such special
treatment, and because the two men
looked quite a bit alike, there's a
fairly good argument to be made that it
was Bushrod who was the father of
Westford. Now, either way, take note
that what we're dealing with here is
even if violence was not involved,
because in cases where the man is an
enslaver and the woman is an enslaved
person, there can be no such thing as
consent. Which, although horrible, needs
to be recognized as being a part of US
history, just like slavery itself. In
fact, the practice was so common that
most African American descendants of
slavery today have about 20 to 25%
European DNA. The other thing we can be
almost certain of is that whether it was
George Washington or Bushrod Washington
or some other Washington, the father of
Westford was in fact a male-line
Washington. Which means that his
descendants definitely belong on this
tree. The most famous descendant of
Westford was his grandson, George
William Ford, who was one of America's
very first Buffalo Soldiers, meaning
that he belonged to an all-black
military unit. George went on to manage
several national cemeteries and served
as a major in the Spanish-American War.
Moving forward to today, here's a photo
of some Westford descendants that got
together for a reunion just last year.
So, maybe in some alternative timeline
in which King Bashaud ended slavery and
made Westford his heir, the king or
queen of America today would be one of
these people.
But, we're not done yet because there
are several more branches of the tree to
look at. But, before we do that, I want
to point out that if you're interested
in US history, you'll definitely want to
check out our new timeline of US
history, which is available as a poster
from our website usefulcharts.com.
It shows how and when each state was
formed, as well as providing lots of
other important information, such as key
events and which party held the House,
Senate, and Presidency at any given
time. We also have a timeline for
European history and world history, as
well as lots of family trees covering
Roman emperors, European monarchs, and
Asian monarchs. Again, if you're
interested in learning more about any of
these posters, just head over to
usefulcharts.com
or simply click the link in the
description or pinned comment. Okay,
let's now return to the family tree of
George Washington.
Notice that on this new version of the
tree, I've shown six different branches
instead of just three. I chose to do
this in order to highlight the fact that
in his last will and testament, the
first president named six executors, one
for each major branch of his family. The
six were William Washington,
representing his half-brother
Augustine's line, his wife Martha,
representing the Parke Custis line,
Lawrence Lewis, representing his sister
Betty's line, George Steptoe Washington,
representing his brother Samuel's line,
Bushrod Washington, representing John's
line, and finally Samuel Thornton
Washington, representing his brother
Charles line.
Now, of these six executors, two ended
up being the main ones, Bushrod and
Lawrence Lewis, who I should point out
ended up marrying Nelly Parke Custis.
So, not only was Lewis the nephew of
George Washington, he was also his
son-in-law, albeit through adoption. On
top of this, after George Washington's
presidency, Lewis became Washington's
personal secretary, which resulted in
the two men becoming quite close.
Because of these reasons, Lewis felt
almost certain that it was he who was
going to inherit Mount Vernon. But, of
course, as we already know, he didn't.
It went to Bushrod instead, which led to
a great deal of resentment on the part
of Lewis. However, according to Martha,
George Washington had two versions of
his will, and near the end of his life,
he instructed her to throw one into the
fire and to use the other one. So, maybe
in that other will, Lawrence Lewis did
inherit Mount Vernon. If that will had
been the one saved, and if George
Washington had been king, what then?
Well, according to my research, the
senior most descendant in this line
would be a certain Charles Conrad Lewis
III. Okay, I now want to return to the
Parke Custis line for a moment, because
G.W.P. Custis actually had at least one
other daughter named Maria, whom he
eventually acknowledged as his own. You
see, Maria's mother was a woman named
Ariana Carter, who had been born
enslaved, held in bondage by Martha
Washington. Later, both Arianna and her
daughter Maria continued to be enslaved
by GW P. Custis, who by that time had
inherited the land, which is today the
Arlington National Cemetery, where he
ordered the construction of Arlington
House. Now, interestingly, only two
couples have ever been married at
Arlington House. The first was Maria
Carter and her husband Charles Syphax,
who were both enslaved at the time.
Although a few years later, Maria and
her children were given their freedom,
as well as 17 acres of land at
Arlington. The only other couple to be
married at Arlington House was Maria's
half-sister Mary and Robert E. Lee. They
ended up inheriting the place, but lost
it during the Civil War, when it was
taken over by the Union. Today,
Arlington House is known as the Robert
E. Lee Memorial. Charles and Maria had
10 children, including William, who
after the war became president of the
board of trustees for colored schools in
Washington, and John, who served as one
of the first black members of the
Virginia House of Delegates. By the 20th
century, the Syphax family had grown to
become one of the most prominent black
families in the country, made up of
professors, doctors, civil rights
activists, business leaders, veterans,
and at least one congressman. So,
interestingly, of all the branches of
the Washington family, it is this one
that became the most aristocratic, even
though they've obviously never held any
noble titles.
Okay, I now want to look at the Samuel
line, because since Samuel was the
eldest full brother of George
Washington, it is the current
descendants of Samuel who are often said
to be the closest living relatives of
the first president. So, I've already
pointed out George Steptoe, who was one
of the six executors of George
Washington's will. Well, he had two sons
who were recently the subjects of a
scientific study that helped determine
the first president's exact
Y-chromosomal haplotype. You see, DNA
was collected from their remains, as
well as from one of John's current
male-line descendants named Samuel
Walter Washington. And through the study
published in 2024, it was determined
that George Washington's Y-chromosomal
haplogroup is R-U152.
So, basically, if you get the same
result on a DNA test, it means that both
you and George Washington have a
male-line ancestor in common who lived
around 2500 BCE in Europe. Take note
that George Steptoe's male-only line
eventually died out. So, these days, the
closest living relative of the first
president is considered to be the most
senior male descendant of this person
here. In 1976, an NBC news program
determined this to be Paul Washington.
However, Paul passed away in 2014. So,
the distinction is now held by his son
Richard. Okay, so the only two lines
that I haven't yet talked about in this
video are the Charles line and the
Augustine line. I wasn't able to find
anything new or interesting about either
of those, but if you know anything, do
share it with us in the comments. I will
point out that the senior-most person in
the Augustine line, Brian Kelly, is
still living, so there's been no change
there.
Okay, so for the remainder of the video,
>> [clears throat]
>> I thought I'd mention how a few other
famous people connect to the tree. The
first is Denzel Washington, probably the
most famous person today with the last
name Washington. Now, while I haven't
been able to confirm this through solid
genealogical research. There are several
amateur trees out there, including one
on the UsefulCharts subreddit, which
claim that Denzel's
great-great-grandfather
was the son of Bushrod Corbin Washington
and a woman he enslaved named Louisa.
Again, I haven't been able to find any
primary records to back this up. So, if
anyone does know more about this, do let
us know in the comments. However, I will
say that because George Washington was
so famous, after emancipation, a lot of
former enslaved people chose to take the
name Washington as a surname, regardless
of whether or not they had actually been
held in bondage by the Washington
family. This practice was so common that
today around 90% of people with the last
name Washington are black Americans with
no close biological connection to the
first president. As for other US
presidents that George Washington is
related to, the closest would be the
fourth president, John Madison, although
it's not by blood. You see, George
Steptoe Washington, who I mentioned
earlier, married Lucy Payne, and Lucy
Payne was the sister of Dolly Payne,
better known as First Lady Dolly
Madison. The closest blood relative who
also became president would be William
Harrison. Earlier, I did a video about
how 20 US presidents are related, and in
that video, I showed how the two
Harrisons descend from Ann Washington,
who was the sister of Lawrence
Washington, the great-great-grandfather
of George Washington. So, that makes the
first president and the ninth president
fourth cousins twice removed. There is,
however, another famous US general that
is fairly closely related to George
Washington, and that is George Patton.
You see, George Washington had an aunt
named Mildred Washington, and if we go
seven generations down from her, we come
to the famous World War II leader. Now,
some conspiracy theorists claim that a
certain other famous president is
actually the son of George Patton due to
the fact that the two men look somewhat
alike. But, I'm not going to go there
because trying to find out who would be
king of America if George Washington had
been made king is already a really big
stretch.
Okay, so that was another look at the
family tree of the first president.
Again, if you're interested in US
history or just history in general, do
check out the posters that we sell over
at usefulcharts.com.
Thanks for watching.